# Norman Wall





7500 E Deer Valley Scottsdale, AZ 85255



Cell Phone: (480) 388-9409



norm@normanwall.com



www.normanwall.com



Printer Friendly Version



Word Version



PDF Version



# Summary

Mr. Wall is a driven, process-oriented, results-focused quality management leader. His qualifications span multiple facets of Information Technology. He has worked closely with customers, business partners, solution architects, program managers, and quality management staff to deliver quality applications with reduced cost and on-time delivery. In his recent role Norman has taken on several roles for US Airways, including: Senior Manager Quality Assurance, Program QA Manager, QA Lead Engineer, and Tools and Automation Specialist. He is an excellent leader with exceptional analytical and technical skills; as well as verbal and written communication skills. He has 12 years experience with Quality Assurance, coupled with 8 years experience leading Quality Assurance projects. His experience in quality management covers the whole gamut ranging from process and metrics, test estimation, test planning and execution, all the way to advanced test automation and performance test. He also has a strong background in practicing Agile principles in addition to more conventional waterfall methodologies, as well as being a proven resource manager.



# Accomplishments



#### US Airways

- Provided leadership in the formation of the Quality Management Office, an organization responsible for setting standards and communicating best practices across the IT organization.
- Introduced standards and tools for test automation, load & performance testing, defect management, metrics and reporting.
- Architected test automation solutions and frameworks and led teams of test engineers and test analysts performing development work and test execution.
- Developed custom automation tools for interacting with the mainframe reservations system for the purpose of creating and managing baseline data for test automation.
- Introduced Build Verification Testing (BVT) into the build process for the various SOA web services.
- Created standardized defect metrics processes across the IT organization for consistent measurement and reporting to upper management.
- Built, maintained, and administered the Quality Management Office SharePoint portal.

#### Pegasus Solutions, Inc.

- Developed, maintained, and supported a keyword-driven test automation framework, Ultra Slim Test (UST).
- Researched, evaluated, and implemented test automation solutions using HP's (Mercury) WinRunner, Quick Test Pro, and Quality Center products.

5/23/2012 10:49 PM 1 of 4

- Developed parsing applications which were used company-wide to analyze transaction logs and request/response messages.
- Led a transition team that migrated helpdesk job functions from Utell (Omaha, NE) to Pegasus Data Services (Scottsdale, AZ).
- Coded and implemented fully-automated SQL Reporting System. Runs across several Reservation and Hotel Database Systems.

### Cendant Corp.

- Featured in the ComputerWorld article "Linux Checks in at Hotel Chain", by Todd R. Weiss, Nov. 19 2001.
- Key member of Cendant's Phoenix to New Jersey relocation team, which involved movement of personnel, information, and systems.
- Aided in the planning, construction, hiring, training, and support of Technical Support Customer Contact Centers in Mumbai (India), and Saint John (New Brunswick, Canada).
- Developed and maintained technical support self-help knowledgebase website.



# Work Experience

U·S AIRWAYS

#### 2012-Present - US Airways - Tempe, AZ - Senior Manager Quality Assurance

- Provide leadership across the enterprise for test automation and performance test projects.
- Develop and maintain standards, processes and best practices in respect to test automation.
- Serve as chief architect for test automation frameworks and custom testing utilities.
- Support internal clients by providing test automation and performance test services for critical programs and projects.
- Resource manage and lead team of 10 automation and performance engineers.
- Responsible for recruiting top talent for Quality Engineer positions across the enterprise.

### 2010-2012 - US Airways - Tempe, AZ - Lead Engineer

- Provided leadership across the IT organization for the test automation practice in terms of tools, standards and best practices.
- Architected test automation solutions & frameworks across a variety of platforms including various mainframes, Oracle, Web and SOA Web Services.
- Led teams of test engineers and test analysts on business critical projects.
- Provided training, mentoring and support to test engineers in respect to the test automation tools and the applications under test.
- Interviewed and participated in the recruitment of new employees and contractors.
- Managed projects by creating extensive project plans, estimates, master test plans, assigning tasks, coordinating meetings, and publishing metrics and summary reports.

## 2009-2009 - US Airways - Tempe, AZ - Automation Analyst

- Developed test automation solutions for web services, mainframe, and 16-bit GUI application.
- Standardized Quality Assurance practices across multiple development/project teams.
- Implemented Agile (Scrum) software development methodologies through education, documentation and mentoring.
- Trained QA staff on software testing fundamentals, Agile (Scrum) principles, and QA best practices.
- Developed & maintained defect tracking work item for Microsoft Team Foundation Server (TFS).
- Created and executed functional and non-functional automated test cases that exercise business logic and requirements.
- Authored and published templates used for test planning, test case design, and metrics/reporting.



2007-2009 - Pegasus Solutions, Inc. - Scottsdale, AZ - Senior Quality Assurance Engineer

2 of 4 5/23/2012 10:49 PM

- Managed and coordinated Quality Assurance efforts on multiple applications, including: reviewing requirements, developing effective test plans and test cases, test execution, defect tracking, and reporting
- Defined comprehensive QA methodologies and introduced best practice processes and procedures within the Software Development Lifecycle (SDL).
- Authored and executed concise functional and non-functional black box, regression, and user acceptance test cases (leveraging both manual and automated test scripts).
- Collaborated with development and led offshore test resources to ensure projects ran on-time and that software was delivered with exceptional quality in an Agile (Scrum) environment.
- Developed and maintained in-house test automation framework, Ultra Slim Test (UST).
- Responsible for ensuring standards and processes complied with ITIL guidelines.
- Administered HP Quality Center server and Microsoft Office Sharepoint Server (MOSS).
- Created and maintained departmental procedural documentation, user guides, and knowledge base.
- 2003-2007 Pegasus Solutions, Inc. Scottsdale, AZ Senior Automation Analyst
- Automated test scripts using HP Interactive's WinRunner and Quick Test Pro software.
- Developed various test automation solutions for Windows / Unix / Web applications using VB6 / VB.NET / ShellScript / Perl / Ruby.
- Administered HP Quality Center server.
- Wrote functional test scripts and performed User Acceptance Testing (UAT) on customer-facing software.
- Trained and mentored staff on QA methodologies, QA processes and HP testing products.
- Participated in code reviews and inspections with Business Analysts and Developers.



#### 1999-2003 - Cendant Corp. - Parsippany, NJ - Technical Support Supervisor

- Key member of Cendant's relocation strategy team for the Technical Support Call Center(s).
- Performed User Acceptance Testing (UAT) on hardware and software prior to deployment.
- Responsible for developing software upgrade & migration processes.
- Conducted training and created documentation for the Technical Support Call Center(s).
- Carried out reporting and data analysis for upper management.
- Provided field services and on-call support to regional Customer Contact Centers and Customers.
- Developed software recovery images using Norton Ghost for Windows & Linux platforms.
- Basic programming, including: Linux shell scripting, VB, DOS batch processing, & C+.



# Education



#### 1997-1998 - Arizona State University

- Completed freshman curriculum including general studies.
- Studied basic computing, programming, and digital design.
- Learned how to effectively work in a team environment.



# Certifications

- Neudesic Agile/Scrum Essentials
- CompTIA A+ / Networks + / Linux +
- HP WinRunner, Quick Test Pro & Quality Center Administration
- HP Performance Center Administration

5/23/2012 10:49 PM 3 of 4



# Computer Skills

#### Software:

- Test Automation: Quick Test Pro (QTP), WinRunner, SoapUI, Watin, Watir, nUnit, Microsoft Webtest, Microsoft Coded UI Test, Auto-It, Selenium, Fitnesse
- Performance Testing: LoadRunner, Performance Center, LoadUI, OpenSTA, JMETER
- Quality Assurance: Quality Center, Rally, MS Team Foundation Server (TFS)
- Development: MS Visual Studio 2005/2008/2010, MS Team Foundation Server (TFS), MS Biztalk Server 2009
- Operating Systems: MS-DOS, Win95/98/NT/2k/XP/Vista/7, Linux, Unix
- Servers: Win2k-2k8 Server, Active Directory, IIS, SharePoint (MOSS), MS Project Server
- Databases: MS SQL Server / Access, Informix SQL, Oracle 9i/10g, MySQL
- CRM: SAP / Oracle
- Network Monitoring: What's Up, NetlQ
- Remote Access: PCAnywhere, Terminal Services, DameWare, VNC, Kermit, TeraTerm, NetTerm, Putty
- Disk Imaging: Symantec Norton Ghost, Acronis Truelmage, Drive Image Pro
- Virtual Machines: VirtualPC, VMWare
- Incident Tracking: Heat, BMC Remedy / ITSM / Service Desk Express, BugZilla
- Internet Authoring: MS FrontPage, Adobe Dreamweaver / Fireworks
- Office Productivity: MS Word / Excel / Access / PowerPoint / Visio / Project / Outlook
- Graphic Design: Adobe Illustrator / PageMaker / PhotoShop / Image Ready / Gimp

### Languages:

- VBScript / VB6 / VB.NET / C# / Perl / Ruby / Groovy / Shell Scripting / TSL
- HTML / CSS / XML / XPath / XQuery / ASP.NET / PHP / SSI / JavaScript / Java



# References

Available Upon Request!

© 2012 NormanWall.com. Last Modified on 5/23/2012 at 22:43.

5/23/2012 10:49 PM